Antoine Simoulin, PhD

antoine.simoulin@gmail.com













For the last five years, I worked as a senior data scientist for Quantmetry, a consulting agency in Paris, France. Parallel to that, I continued to strengthen my technical background as Quantmetry sponsored my PhD at the Laboratoire de Linguistique Formelle from Paris Cité University. By combining these two profiles, I am able to translate complex technical problems into long-term objectives, realistic roadmaps, and rational solutions. I conducted multiple data sciences projects for large companies and deployed effective solutions in production. My role went beyond implementation since I contributed from ideation, framing, deployment, to monitoring.

Education



University of Paris Cité

PhD, Computer Science

My PhD entitled, Sentence embeddings and their relation with sentence structures, focuses on Natural language Processing methods for building sentence embeddings. Advised by Prof. Benoit Crabbé, member of LLF lab.



École Polytechnique

Dual master program (MSc), Data Science

The leading French research, academics, and innovation institution.



ENSTA Paris

Master of science (MSc), Simulation and Mathematical Engineering

French engineering school accessible through selective *classe préparatoire*. Last year advised by Prof. Pierre Carpentier, director of UMA lab.

Work Experiences



Quantmetry

Senior data scientist, NLP

Together with a data-science team of business and technical consultants, I participated in multiple projects to automate or optimize processes. I led end-to-end projects for real-world problems, such as putting neural models in production for classifying, summarizing, and automating email replies in one of the largest French insurance companies.



Crédit Agricole Corporate and Investment Banking

Quantitative analyst intern

I implemented and improved Monte-Carlo's algorithms using CUDA on graphic card for the capital calculation of an internal insurance.

New York, USA Sept. 2015 –

Aug. 2016

Paris, France Feb. 2019 -

Paris, France

2016 - 2017

Paris, France 2013 - 2017

Paris, France

Apr. 2017 -

July 2022

July 2022

Skills

Languages **Programming** Skills

French: Native; English: Fluent (TOEIC 965/990); German: Working knowledge In-depth knowledge of Python, working knowledge C, C++, and familiar with R, Matlab

In-depth knowledge of SQL, and working knowledge of Hadoop, Spark

In-depth knowledge of Linux/Unix/Shell environments

Office & Web In-depth knowledge of Microsoft Office. Basic understanding of web design: HTML, CSS

Research Interests

My PhD, entitled *Sentence embeddings and their relation with sentence structures*, studies how neural networks compose text units to build sentence embeddings. I apply linguistic insights to neural network architectures. I design and implement dynamic architectures following tree or graph syntactic patterns. I aim to quantify the impact of linguistic bias on neural network architectures and how compositionality might be leveraged through the network structure. Along with linguistics, my work involves implementing complex structured neural networks as well as pre-training large language models at scale such as a version of GPT-2 for French with over a billion parameters.

2022

Unifying Parsing and True Structured Models for Congreting Sentance Sementic Personantations

Publications

Unifying Parsing and Tree-Structured Models for Generating Sentence Semantic Representations NAACL 2022, Student Research Workshop Antoine Simoulin, Benoit Crabbé	2022
How Many Layers and Why? An Analysis of the Model Depth in Transformers ACL 2021, Student Research Workshop Antoine Simoulin, Benoit Crabbé	2021
Contrasting Distinct Structured Views to Learn Sentence Embeddings EACL 2021, Student Research Workshop Antoine Simoulin, Benoit Crabbé	2021
Generative Pre-trained Transformer in (French) TALN 2021: Traitement Automatique des Langues Naturelles Antoine Simoulin, Benoit Crabbé	2021
Unifying Parsing and Tree-Structured Models for Generating Sentence Semantic Representations In submission Antoine Simoulin, Benoit Crabbé	2021
Deep Learning : des usages contrastés dans le monde socio-économique Statistique et Société, 8: 55-108 R. Adon, F. Arthur, G. Baquiast, G. Hochard, A. Kaid Gherbi, A. Nègre, A. Simoulin et al.	2021
An innovative solution for breast cancer textual big data analysis In submission N. Thiebaut, A. Simoulin, K. Neuberger, I. Ibnouhsein, N. Bousquet, N. Reix, S. Molière, C. Mathelin	2020
Impact du dépistage : une expérience française Mise à jour du Collège National des Gynécologues et Obstétriciens Français C. Mathelin, J. Colin, S. Molière, A. Fleury, C. Linck, M. Paté, C. Guldenfels, A. Simoulin, et al.	2017

Teaching

Natural language processing (2020 - 2022)

Graduate level course in natural language processing (NLP) at Paris Cité University. The course includes 7 sessions (course and lab) and introduces statistical models (TF-IDF, Bag-of-Words, LDA, Embeddings, language models) for NLP. Around 25 students from the mathematics department followed the course each year.

Talks and Presentations

Pre-trained neural networks for text generation and their implications

Apr. 2021

Machine Learning Meetup, Epitech engineering school, Nantes France

Around 30 students and professionals in the field of data science attended the talk. I presented my paper about the first large pre-trained generative model in French.

Implementing and deploying natural language processing projects

Dec. 2019

AI Paris, France

Around 800 professionals in the field of data science attended the presentation. We presented the project of emails classification at MAIF and the challenges to deploy a project in production.

Melusine open-source release

Dec. 2019

BigData Paris, France

Open source release of Melusine, a library for emails processing. Around 80 professionals in the field of data science attended the presentation.

Senometry project: analysis of textual medical records for structured data extraction

May 2018

NLP Meetup, Paris, France

Presentation to around 40 professionals in the field of data science. The research project consists in using NLP methods to automatically analyze data from medical records.

Open Source Contributions



GPT-fr is a French large pre-trained language model for French. The base version, equivalent to OpenAI GPT in English, includes above 1B parameters.



PyTree implements tree-structured neural networks in PyTorch. The package provides highly generic implementations as well as efficient batching methods. The project was listed among the winners of the PyTorch Annual Hackathon 2021.



Sentence embedding pre-trained model trained on 1B sentence pairs. The project was listed among the winners during the Hugging Face Community week using JAX/Flax for NLP & CV 2021.



Melusine is a high-level Python library for email classification and feature extraction developed by Quantmetry and MAIF.